Good morning, today we will have the first
module of machine learning part C.
I will talk about hypothesis space and inductive
bias will give you brief introduction to this,
so that when we talk about a different machine
learning algorithms, we can refer to this
discussion.
So, as we have seen that in inductive learning
or prediction, we have given a examples of data
And the example are of the form as we have
seen x, y, where x for a particular instance
x comprises of the values of the different
features of that instance; and y is the output attribute
And we can also think of that as being given
x and f(x).
So, if you assume that the output of an instance
is a function of the input vector input feature
vector; and this is the function that we are
trying to learn, we are given x, f(x) pairs
as examples.
And we want to learn x.
For a classification problem, in the earlier
class, we talked about two types of supervised
learning problems - classification and regression
depending on whether the output attributes
type is discrete valued or continuous valued.
In classification problem, this function f(x)
is discrete; in regression, the function f
(x) is continuous.
And we can also apart from classification
and regression, in some cases we may want
to find out the probability of a particular
value of y.
So, for those problems, where we look at probability
estimation, our f(x) is the probability of
x; so this is the type of inductive learning
problems that we are looking at.
Why do we call this inductive learning?
We are given some data and we are trying to
do induction to try to identify a function,
which can explain the data.
So, induction as oppose to deduction, unless
we can see all the instances all the possible
data points or we make some restrictive assumption
about the language in which the hypothesis
is expressed or some bias, this problem is
not well defined so that is why it is called
an inductive problem.
Then in the last class, we talked about features.
So when we say we have to learn a function,
it is a function of the features; so instances
are described in terms of features.
So, features are properties that describe
each instance; and each instance can be described
in a quantitative manner using features.
And often we have multiple features so we
have what we call a feature vector, for example,
for a particular instance we may be or a particular
task we may be describing all the instances
in terms of ten features, so the feature vector
will be a one-dimensional vector of size 10.
Now, based on this we can define a features
space.
Suppose, for simplicity, let us assume that
there are two features; and we can say that
the features are x 1 and x 2.
In general, we can have n number of features
we have two features the features define a
two-dimensional space if we have n features
the define an n dimensional space if you take
a particular instance let us say d 1 is an
instance and for d 1 x 1 equal to 2, x 2 equal
to 5.
So, let us say x 1 is 2 here and x 2 is 5
here.
So, this is d 1 so d 1 can be thought of as
a point in this feature space point in the
two dimensional feature space or you can think
of it as a vector in this space so each instance
is a point in the feature space.
Now, let us look at a classification problem.
And let us say that it is a two class classification
problem so we have given a number of instances
for examples some of which belong to class
1, the others belong to class 2, so there
are two class classification problems.
We have two types of instances those belonging
to class 1 and those belonging to class 2.
You are given a training set which comprises
a subset of the instances, some of them are
marked class 1, some of them are marked class
2, and we can say that class 1 is positive
and class 2 as negative.
So, we find that we can map different points
in this feature space, let us say these are
the positive points.
And we have some other points in this feature
space which are negative points.
Now, what we want to do is we want to learn
a function, so that based on the function,
we want the function to predict whether a
new instance, which is given to you.
Suppose, this is a new instance, which is
given to you, we want to know whether this
should be positive or negative.
In order to do this, we have to learn a function
or the function could be a particular curve
or a line, which separates the positive from
the negative instances.
For example, the function that we learn could
be this function.
And we can say that any point which lies to
this side of the function is positive any
point which lies to this side of the function
is negative.
And since this yellow point lies to the left
of the function it is negative, so this is
what inductive learning is about.
So, let us look at the slide in this slide,
which I have taken from a slide by Jesse Davis
of University of Washington.
We can see a feature space is described in
terms of the positive and negative examples.
The green pluses are the positive points;
the red minuses are the negative points.
Now this is a particular instance, for which
x 1 is 0.5, x 2 is 2.8 and the label of this
instance is positive.
Now these question mark points are the test
points.
And we are asked to find out what should be
the class of those points may be positive
or negative in the prediction problem.
So, in order to answer the prediction problem
we have to come up with the function, for
example, let us say we come up with this pink
function pink line, and we say lines points
that lie to the right of the pink line is
negative the points which lie to the left
of the pink line is positive.
In this case, this point and this point will
be marked positive; and this point and this
point will be marked negative.
So, this pink line is the function that we
have come up with and so this is the hypothesis
or function that we used to do our prediction.
Now, we could have instead of this particular
line, we could have hypothesized other functions.
So, all these are possible functions, which
we could have found.
And the set of all such legal functions that
we could have come up with they define the
hypothesis space.
In a particular learning problem, you first
defined the hypothesis space that is the class
of function that you are going to consider
then given the data points, you try to come
up with the best hypothesis given the data
that you have.
We have briefly talked about in the last module
about how a function is represented so as
we have discussed a function is represented
in terms of features.
There are two things that we need in order
to describe a function, we have to decide
the features of the vocabulary, and we have
to decide the function class or the type of
function or the language of the function that
we will have to we will be using.
So, based on the features and the language,
we can define our hypothesis space.
Various types of representations have been
considered for making predictions.
For example, we just saw that we could have
a linear function to act as a discriminator
between two classes, we will in a subsequent
class, we will look at a representation by
using a structure, which we called a decision
tree.
Where at a decision tree is a tree, where
at every node, we take a decision based on
the value of an attribute.
And based on that, we go to different branches,
so at every node, we make a decision based
on the value of an attribute and every leaf
node is labeled by the value of y.
So, decision tree is a type of representation;
linear function is one type of representation.
You could also have multivariate linear function
linear function you can have neural networks.
These are some examples of representation
and we have some examples in the slide here.
A decision tree, a linear function, a multivariate
linear function, a single layer perceptron
- the basic unit of a neural network, a multi
layer neural network; these are some of the
representations that we will talk about later
in this class.
So, once you have chosen the features and
the language or the class of functions, what
you have is a hypothesis space.
So, hypothesis space is the space of all legal
hypothesis, is a set of all legal hypothesis
that you can describe using the features that
you have chosen, and the language that you
have chosen.
And this is the set from which the learning
algorithm will pick a hypothesis.
So, hypothesis space we may represent a hypothesis
space by H and the learning algorithm outputs
a hypothesis h belonging to H, this is the
output of a learning algorithm.
So, capital H denotes all legal hypothesis,
all possible outputs by the learning algorithm.
Given the training set given the particular
data points, the learning algorithm will come
up with one of the hypothesis in the hypothesis
space which hypothesis it comes up with will
depend on the data, and it also will depend
on what type of restrictions or biases that
we have imposed, which we will describe later.
So, supervised learning, we can think of is
a device which explore the hypothesis space
or which searches the hypothesis space in
order to find out one of the hypothesis which
satisfies certain criteria.
Now first some more terminology before we
proceed.
We have already talked about an example as
x, y the value of the input and the value
of the output x, y pair.
Training data is a set of examples
is a collection of a examples, which have
been observed by the learning algorithm or
which is input to the learning algorithm.
We have instance space or feature space, which
describes all possible instances, so if we
have two features x 1 and x 2; let us say
x 1 takes value between 0 and 100, x 2 takes
value between 0 and 50; and all points in
this plane can describe an instance, so this
is the instance space.
So, instance space is the set of all possible
objects that can be described by the features.
And we are trying to learn a concept c.
Let us think of a classification problem where
we have a particular class that we are trying
to learn.
So, let us think of a two class classification
problem, we can define one of the classes
is positive, the other is negative, we can
think of the positive examples as the concept
which we are trying to learn.
So, out of all possible objects that we can
describe in the instance space, subsets of
those objects are positive that is they belong
to the concept.
So, the concept c can be a subset of the instance
space X, so which define the positive points.
C is unknown to us and this is what we are
trying to find out.
In order to find out c, we are trying to find
a function f, so f is what we are trying to
learn.
What is f?
f is a function which maps every input X to
an output Y.
Now what is the difference between c and f,
f is used to be a function used to describe
the concept they may be same, they may be
different, because f is defined by the language
and the features that you have chosen.
So, this is a certain difference between f
and c.
Now, what you are trying to do in learning
is given a hypothesis space h.
You are trying to come up with the hypothesis
small h belonging to the hypothesis H that
approximates f.
You want to find h that approximates f based
on the training data that you have been given.
Now the set of hypothesis that can be produced
can be restricted further by specifying a
language bias.
So, hypothesis space defines all possible
set of hypothesis, you can restrict hypothesis
by defining some bias.
So, you can specify some constraints on the
language or some preferences.
So, bias is of two types, bias can be in terms
of constraints or the bias can be in terms
of preferences.
We will define them more precisely soon, but
what we mean by constraints is suppose your
features are Boolean variables, now if you
say that you want to consider only Boolean
functions, which are conjunctions of monomials,
so that is providing a bias or the language.
If you say that you want a function, which
is simpler then you are putting a preference
bias.
So, we will talk about this later.
So, given these definitions in a learning
problem, the input is a training set let us
say S, S is a subset of the instance space,
X is the instance space, which comprises of
all possible instances and the training examples
that you are given is a subset of this.
And output, you are required to output, a
hypothesis small h belonging to the hypothesis
space capital H, so this is for a classification
problem.
So, let me rub the board before we proceed.
Now, let us look at hypothesis space.
Now suppose we look at functions just to take
an example.
We take features which are Boolean.
Suppose, x 1, x 2, x 3, x 4 are four features,
and they are Boolean features the value of
the features are true or false.
Now, if there are four Boolean features, and
how many possible instances can you have,
in a particular instance x 1 can be true or
false 0 or 1, x 2 can be 0 or 1, x 3 can be
0 or 1, x 4 can be 0 or 1.
So, there is 1 to the power 4 or 16 possible
instances.
So, number of possible instances is 2 to the
power 4 or 16.
Now how many possible function are there,
how many Boolean functions are possible.
So, what is a function, a function will classify
some of the points as positive others as negative
out of the 16 points, so that means the number
of functions is the number of possible subsets
of this 16 instances.
So, how many possible subsets are there, there
are 2 to the power 16 subsets or 2 to the
power 2 to the power 4 subsets.
Instead of 4 Boolean variables as feature,
if you had N Boolean features, then the number
of possible instances will be 2 to the power
N. And number of possible function will be
2 to the power 2 to the power N.
So, this is the size of the hypothesis space.
As you can see the hypothesis space is very
large, and it is not possible to look at every
hypothesis individually in order to select
the best hypothesis that you want.
So, what do you do you put some restrictions
on the hypothesis space, you can put some
restrictions.
So, you select a hypothesis language.
So, this hypothesis language may be an unrestricted
language, for example, all possible Boolean
functions or may be a restricted language.
We have seen already some examples of hypothesis
languages as decision tree, linear functions,
neural networks etcetera or there could be
polynomial function, linear function, or there
could be conjunction Boolean formulas, CNF
Boolean formulas, unrestricted Boolean formulas
so you choose a hypothesis language.
The hypothesis language if you restrict the
hypothesis language, the hypothesis language
reflects bias, so this reflects a bias or
inductive bias of the learner.
Now, so let us define formally what is inductive
bias.
So, when we choose a hypothesis space, we
need to make some assumptions.
And there as I said there are two types of
assumptions that you can make.
You can put restrictions on the type of functions
that is you can say instead of considering
all Boolean formulas, we are going to consider
only conjunctive Boolean formulas.
You can say that for regression problem, you
can say that we are looking at linear functions,
or you can say that we can look at fourth
degree polynomials or nth degree polynomials
or we can say we look as any polynomial.
So, specifying the form of the function is
called restriction bias.
The second type of bias that you can use is
preference bias, where given a particular
language that you have chosen you say that
I am considering all possible polynomials,
but I will prefer polynomials of lower degree.
So, you can say that I am considering all
possible Boolean functions, but I want a Boolean
function which can be described in small size.
So, you can put different types of bias on
your learning algorithm.
So, inductive learning means to come up with
the general function from training examples.
Given some training examples, you want to
generalize.
So, you construct a hypothesis h, you are
given some training examples which comes from
a concept c, and you want to find out a hypothesis
h.
You can come up with the hypothesis that is
consistence with all the training examples
given, then such hypothesis are called consistence
hypothesis; it is sometimes not possible to
come up with the consistence hypothesis and
sometimes we will not come up with the consistence
hypothesis.
But even when you are coming up with the consistence
hypothesis, given a hypothesis space and given
a training data multiple possible consistence
hypothesis can be there, and you have to select
which one of them you want to output based
on your preference bias.
The hypothesis that you want to output is
most often, you are guided by you want to
come up with the hypothesis that generalizes
well over the unseen examples, you form your
hypothesis based on the training data.
But you want come up with the hypothesis that
does not just do well on the training data,
but is likely to do well on unseen data.
Now inductive learning is an ill post problem.
If you do not look at all, suppose, your hypothesis
space is all Boolean formulas, and if you
do not look at all the 2 to the power N possible
examples if you look at a subset of those
examples multiple possible hypothesis is possible,
and they have they will behave differently
with the rest of the examples.
So, you cannot come up with the correct hypothesis
by logical being by you know which is which
is guaranteed to be true without seeing all
the training examples.
So, inductive learning is a ill post problem,
you are looking for generalization guided
by some bias or some criteria.
So, why you are being able to generalize,
it is based on a assumption we call this assumption
the inductive learning hypothesis.
The hypothesis states that a hypothesis h
is found to approximate the target function
c well over a sufficiently large set of training
examples.
So, if you come up with a hypothesis which
has a low training error over a sufficiently
large training set you expect that hypothesis
to do well on unseen examples.
So, this is the inductive learning hypothesis.
And learning can be looked upon as searching
through the hypothesis space.
Based on the training examples and the bias
that you have imposed, there are different
types of bias for example, one classical bias
is a bias called Occam’s Razor.
Occam’s razor states that you will prefer
the simplest hypothesis.
So, this is a principle or this is a philosophical
principle that if something can be described
in a short language that hypothesis is to
be preferred over a more complex hypothesis.
And there are other types of inductive bias
like minimum description length, like maximum
margin etcetera which will be only which can
be explained, when we talk about the specific
algorithms where such biases is used.
So, in machine learning, you have to come
up with a good hypothesis space, you have
to find an algorithm that works well with
the hypothesis space, you have to come up
with the hypothesis algorithm that works well
with the hypothesis space, and outputs on
hypothesis that is expected to do well over
future data points.
And you have to understand what is the confidence
that you have on the hypothesis and these
are the things that we will discuss.
So, machine learning coming up with a function
is all about doing generalization.
And when you are doing generalization, you
can make some errors.
And the errors are of two types, bias errors
and variance errors.
So, bias as we saw is a restriction on the
hypothesis space or the preference in choosing
hypothesis.
By deciding a particular hypothesis, you impose
a bias.
So, this is error due to incorrect assumptions
or restrictions on the hypothesis space, the
error introduced by that is called bias error.
Variance error is introduced when you have
a small test set, so variance error means
the model that you estimate from different
training sets will differ from each other.
If you come up with the model from some 50
training set, 50 data points, and you take
another 50 data points on the distribution
you can come up with the very different model,
then we say that there is a variance among
the results.
And this point, we will discuss later when
we talk about different learning algorithms.
This is a very important concept, but we will
talk about it when we talk about the algorithms,
this is overfitting and underfitting.
You may come up with the hypothesis that does
well over the training examples, but does
very poorly over the test examples, and then
we say overfitting has occurred.
Overfitting comes from using very complex
functions so you are using too few training
data.
And the reverse of overfitting is underfitting,
if you have a very simple function then it
cannot capture all the nuances of the data.
So, we will talk about details of overfitting
and underfitting when we talk about specific
algorithms.
With this, we come to the end of this module.
Thank you.